i wanted to speak about this suitor
um in the samyuttanikaya 39.16 and and
it's
with us
he's been asked a question
it's a short suit and i'll read it out
quickly vulnerable sariputta
vulnerable sariputta
in this teaching and training in the
stammer and
discipline what is hard to do
what is hard to do
and he answers
the going forth is
difficult to do in this dhamma and
discipline but what's hard to do for someone who
but what's hard to do for someone who
has gone forth
when you've gone forth it's difficult to
be satisfied
contented man oh
yeah it's difficult to be
contented but what's hard what's
difficult to do for someone who's
contented when you're content it's hard to
when you're content it's hard to
practice in line with the teaching
and then you ask
but if a
renunciant practices in line with the
teaching will it take them long to
become a perfected one
and he replies
it won't take them long
i thought it was very nice you know it's
quite simple
it's kind of well
just just go for it
just go for it
you know learn to be content
yeah and practice
and in no long time you have the result
yes yeah
so the um
yeah exactly the contentment needs to be
learned yeah you have to learn how to be
yeah you have to learn how to be
contented because
uh
you know you won't be able to to sustain
practicing in line with the dhamma on
the same level all the time so you're
going to have ups and downs
so the contentment is important for when
you have your downs
you don't go lower than being contented
within the homeless life
so then you can easily and quickly carry
on practicing when it picks up
if you are not contented
with uh with with the life of someone
who has gone forth then
when you experience the downs
the mind will want to go back to like
you know
household life basically
so so that's why it's important to be
contented um whether your practice is
going good or not
whether you're inspired or not
uh contentment is a kind of a basis
that will sort of sustain that state of
having gone forth
uh which of course that means that any
given at any given time the possibility of
at any given time the possibility of
picking up the practice along the right
lines remains there for you you haven't
excluded yourself from it to say to say
like that
what comes to mind is you know a person
who goes forth and
starts the their training of virtue and
sensual strength
it is difficult
but then
yeah so he it's difficult to sustain
having sustained it you know you can
become accomplished in virtue
accomplished in central strand and feel
the joy on account of that
accomplishment you know yeah so
and now you always have that joy to to
sustain you to fall back on you because
you can't fall
you don't fall below that yeah and
that's i think that's exactly yeah
that's those other suttas where the
buddha said like you should
replace the joys of a household life with the
the joys of a household life with the
joys of renunciate life
you should replace the the grief and
sadness of a household life with the
grief and sadness of a renunciated life
so you're still gonna have up ups and
downs but if you're contented with that
life means you have upgraded at least in that
means you have upgraded at least in that
sense
so because joys and um and griefs of a
household life are much
worse much more much more
pressuring
and entangling
proliferated and so on then those offer
an anti-life there are still joys ups
and downs
but they're uh purer say that way
because you are withdrawn from that you
know household life is crowded and he
has the suit to say so
and the lifeguard force is open air yeah
open yeah it's fresh clear it's clean good
good
and i like what you know what is it
difficult to go forth
exactly yeah yeah it's difficult to give up that
yeah yeah it's difficult to give up that
which is familiar to you that which
which you know
that which you're uh
comfortable in
let's say like that so uh
change is unpleasant yeah so it's
difficult to to to undergo such a change
of giving up a household life for
something that you are uncertain about
and something that will
require you to learn how to be contented
with so that's why it's it's it's difficult
so that's why it's it's it's difficult
to to give it up and anybody who has
tried to give it up realizes it's
difficult to give it up
giving it up and going forth
and keeping the precepts virtue you know
taking refuge in the buddha for the rest
of your life so to speak you know i will
maintain this virtue i will maintain the
sanctuary strength
it says you know the buddha says you
know if you do that
you will experience a joy the joy of
being blameless the joy of being
unpolluted yeah eventually
eventually
which you know
once you once you have that
it's um
then it's easier what is
what is
the practice
well yeah of course yeah i mean
in many surveys it said that uh you know
uh
joy arises on the count of unbroken
virtue contentment
contented and joyous mind gets composed
so samadhi is born out of it
um
so yeah it's like a necessary basis it's
part of the practice really
uh learning how to be content uh with
with uh with a how with a homeless life
it's already in a way practicing along
the lines of of the dharma
in terms of
you know you read that you will become
happy and feel a blameless joy if you
and feel a blameless joy if you
maintain your virtue
and which is you know you'll feel a
blameless joy so
so
and you're not really doing anything
you're just not doing
wrong things
and that joy is accessible to you
just reflecting on your sila
sila nusati
that joy is you know experienced
yeah you know you know this i was once dirty
you know you know this i was once dirty
now i'm quite clean but but
but
it's funny how
just that first step
you know the buddha says keep this and
you'll be happy you know you'll feel
this blameless joy that first step is
kind of
not not many people have faith in just
that first step
which is
it's so accessible actually it's so
close that
very lofty pleasure is so close
you know it's accessible yet
it's like i don't have faith in that i'd
rather i'd rather do some something else i'd
i'd rather do some something else i'd
rather do meditation instead
instead
but that's not the first step
yeah so
do you have faith in the buddha
yourself your own ideas of what the
practice is
yeah that's that uh kind of um
lack of clarity that sort of exists
in many people even if they have genuine
intention to practice
um
they don't realize that that
you know you
your your views of what the practice is
what what what's important for the
practice are views affected with ignorance so
are views affected with ignorance so
your practice actually should start by
questioning those views questioning your
motivation uncovering revealing your practice
uncovering revealing your practice
shouldn't start with just taking for
granted the views that you have about
the practice and practicing on account
of them
and many people fall into that trap in a
sense of
they get the idea of what the practice
is
the obviously you know you develop
obviously you know you develop
standpoints of what's important what's
not and then you just they just take it
for granted that that's what the
practice is that's what the buddha was
teaching so they can profess
so they can profess
you know
that their follower of of the of the
buddhist teaching and the dumb and so on
yet as you say exactly the very first
thing that the buddha says you should do
they're kind of overlooked
it's it's it's quite easily done when
your stand points are already far away
from from from what's really important
so that's why like the buddha said the
most blameword thing is the wrong view
that's that's like that's the reason for
you know for everything and wholesome in
a way because if a person were to learn
or just stop actually questioning
themselves rightly in a sense of hold on
yes i have faith that the buddha was
enlightened i faith that the dharma is well
i faith that the dharma is well
expounded
i have faith that if i follow that
dharma i can also you know reach some
stage of enlightenment to free myself
from suffering
so am i actually
following clearly in understanding uh
what the buddha said in practicing on
account of it
or is my idea of you know i'm a good
follower kind of and i have faith in
dharma abstractly but practically i'm
doing something else like what do i put
first am i am i am i doing my meditation for
am i am i am i doing my meditation for
the sake of enlightenment or have i
really developed the unbroken unblemished
developed the unbroken unblemished
aggregate of virtue
whereby i just recollect it and i
experience pleasure and account of it
because that's what buddha said you
should do
and you shouldn't be
doing that meditation before you've done
that well exactly then then you if you
start questioning as to see if you're
actually doing what the buddha said you
should do
uh not doing what you think the buddha
said you should do
so make the effort or if you are
absolutely convinced then again it will
it will do you no harm to re-evaluate it
and if you arrive at the same answers
great but you have to be honest with yourself
but you have to be honest with yourself
so if you are you would see that well
there are certain things that the buddha
said you should do and have i done those
things because yes something as simple
as developing virtue well the buddha
said if you actually develop it rightly
yes the the simply recollecting that
the the simply recollecting that
recollecting the buddha and the sangha
it will it will fill me with joy and
samadhi is that the case
is that the case
when i recollect my virtue am i joyous
am i contented am i sort of withdrawn
from unwholesome state simply on account
of that recollection
well if the answer is no
then your idea of virtue and your
practice of virtue is obviously not
fulfilled it's not fulfilled from the
buddha stand point of view from the
point of view of practicing the dharma
so
you could ignore it and carry on
thinking it's fine or you could just
say to yourself hold on why don't i
fulfill this it is something very
straightforward hard to misunderstand easy to overlook
hard to misunderstand easy to overlook
but hard to misunderstand if you look at
it it's not complex
the reason people don't do it is not
because it's just oh i don't understand
what i'm supposed to do no it's because
they overlook it
they just uh drift and do something else
or do something on top of it instead of
it
or at the expense of it so so that's
that's kind of the point that honesty
and self-reflection and then you would
re-evaluate things you think you know
and again by reading the suitors you
would see quite clearly
what the first thing to do is and as we
said in the opening this you realize
what that is already by developing a
virtue contentment on account of the
contentment on account of the
unblemished aggregate of virtue you are
practicing in line with the dharma so
it's not like oh i'll do that and then
i'll do that that is already doing the
dhamma rightly
because as the buddha said
um even within the five precepts
somebody keeping the five precepts if
they do it in that responsible sense
uh purify it until it's until the
aggregate of that virtue is developed
until he's like oh i have been keeping
the five precepts have not intentionally
uh went against them for a long time the
recognition of that will arise
and would have said so even within those
five presets if a person then recollects
that unblemished five precepts and
virtue recollects the buddha the dhamma and the
recollects the buddha the dhamma and the
sangha that is their unification of mind
that is their samadhi a factual samadhi
arises as a result of it
the aggregate of samadhi comes from that
aggregate of
exactly exactly and that's why that's
why it's samadhi because you're not
doing it
you're not creating it through your own
sort of you know contrived techniques
and so on it's the result of the
aggregate of virtue so it's the result
of your practice
which revolved around
self-control and abstaining from
unwholesome things things rooted in
so you sustain that long enough that
samadhi will follow
samadhi will be a result of it now when
you are composed on a kind of
contentment that arose because of your unbroken
that arose because of your unbroken
virtue
your unbroken virtue will be purified
even further because
you know being composed means not being
as pressured or not being pressured as
much as if
as if
as when you are pressured when you're
not composed and then the mind gets
pulled and pressured by various things
that sort of you have to resist
so composure that arises on account of
the virtue will then feed and help the
virtue and sustain the virtue
yeah so further you can clean
the situation further
you know
abandoning the hindrances you know just
yeah you can then start you can then
start refining it and so on in order to
to refine something first you need to
get rid of the the crude
uh impurities i mean there are many
similarities like purifying the gold you
know you don't just ignore all the junk
around the around the gold dust and then
start purifying the specific no first
you have to get rid of all of that
there is just simply no other way to get
to the refined points
so and that's what i mean they will
become apparent to a person
if they do actually as we say often
start questioning their own motivation
so
okay i want to meditate meditation helps
me i keep the precepts but
okay so so why what do i expect from
meditation what what what do i want to
gain from it because
if i'm keeping the precipice rightly if
i have developed
the aggregate of virtue rightly
that should already be my meditation
that should already be the joy and
gladness a form of composure should already arise
a form of composure should already arise
in my mind simply on account of that yet
here i am
stressed about the environment changing
that will prevent me from meditating and
doing a technique or whatever i'm into
so it's like so that doesn't sound right
it certainly doesn't sound like
something the buddha was describing
and as i said many times before
it is you know it obviously it all stems
from that view
that people kind of just
naturally pick up when they start
learning about buddhism
which is kind of okay so
all the problems all the stress all the
pressure that i'm experiencing
comes because i miss the moment of my
thought or i haven't been focused hard
enough so if i never miss never skip a beat if
so if i never miss never skip a beat if
my mindfulness is every second to a
second if i'm observing my thoughts clearly
if i'm observing my thoughts clearly
constantly evenly all the time
suffering will diminish and i will not
suffer and you read the suttas and the buddha
and you read the suttas and the buddha
said quite clearly that
that's not the reason for suffering the
reason for for one being
affected by pressure stress and
everything else
is
your choices
are still bound are still rooted in
greed aversion delusion
so your choices still actively maintain
the craving
so
presence of craving means presence of
suffering and if you if you start realizing that
and if you if you start realizing that
then you you see that the whole practice
of you know watching moment to moment
moment to moment was basically nothing
other than simply like a coping
mechanism so if you if you realize that
the gateway of all of your problems
it's not like
because your mindfulness skipped a beat
no it's because your body your speech
and your mind
still have actions that are rooted in green
have actions that are rooted in green
diversion delusion on some level and
those actions of greed diversion illusion are
actions of greed diversion illusion are
not subconscious they are not
kind of
uh
extra millisecond quick where you must
have developed this focus to spot them
no they are always on the level of your
conscious choice
which means they're always known
and consequently they're always covered
up
so you need to
that self-honesty you need to uncover
them and admit to yourself what you
already know
and as i said before
if anybody like you know starts this
this self-questioning they will arrive
at that point where they're clearly
going to see
a compromise that they are aware of that
they are making on account of which they
try to compensate
by you know extra commitment to the
meditation to the whatever practice of sila but all
to the whatever practice of sila but all
at the expense of the compromise they're
refusing to give up
and that's
okay if on the other hand i give up the
if on the other hand i give up the
compromise
i don't have to do any of this
that was the missing part for my
aggregate of virtue so if i would have a
day where there is nothing pressuring me
no major event they would be sort of
pulling me for distraction entertainment
and so on
great so i could spend the whole day
then in a mindful state you don't need
to do anything else just keep an eye on
that gateway
yeah content
exactly and that's that's exactly the
four contentment
but if you ignore the fact that you're still
if you ignore the fact that you're still
making compromises on account of greed
aversion distraction
distraction
then everything else will become a
compensation for it but actually it's
it's like it's it seems harder initially
seems like more unpleasant initially
but uh it's not
if you if you take that as a standard
you realize all these other things all
these other burdens of virtue and duty
that you have taken upon yourself as
practice will stop burdening you because they
will stop burdening you because they
will not be your duty anymore your duty
is to not act out of greed aversion
delusion so your duty is to not give in to a
so your duty is to not give in to a
conscious choice
of i'll do this because i'm pressured by
the desire i'll do this because i'm
pressured by ill will i'll do this
because i'm indolent and i want to
distract myself that's it that's all you
need to do from the moment you wake up
to the moment you go to sleep if you do
that you will be unable to break the
precepts you will be unable to be
discontented and you will be unable to not be
and you will be unable to not be
composed
not being unable to not be practicing in
being unable to not be practicing in
line exactly
and then even if you don't think oh now
i should practice uh
in line with the dhamma you will be
practicing in life with the dhamma
and that's what i said oh how do we know
master gautama what is in line with the
dhamma what it isn't well
whatever brings dispassion not passion
whatever uh is is inclined to a solid
should not company towards
disentanglement not entanglement so even
if you don't necessarily want to give up
the house for life just yet the
principle remains the same
you want to keep your mind free from
disturbances in calm well keep an eye on
the doorway of choice of acting out of
great diversion delusion and don't cover
that up
everything else put aside any sense of
oh but i must do this and i must do that
and i must practice on a panasonic and i
was like no you must develop the virtue
that's unblemished unbroken until it
becomes an aggregate on its own
something you're not doing
anymore something that's kind of there because
something that's kind of there because
you've been abstaining from certain
things long enough
and then all you need to do is protect
that virtue
it will give you the context it will
give you the samadhi on account of it
because again the doorway of where all
the problems come in is greater version
delusion it's not lapse of mindfulness
or not enough focusing
you are you're training yourself to see
that doorway clearer and clearer and
clearer and see where all the
defilements are and you're just cleaning
them out yes and and training to see
where that doorway is
it's not on the level of
training your focusing practice they
will then reveal the glimpse of the
doorway the doorway is not a glimpse
it's not a split second it's the entire
context that basically directs your
entire day that's it
so your entire day actions throughout
the day choices you're making are very
conscious things that's where the
doorway is
so you don't need the focusing to see
the doorway you need honesty to see
and then initially like oh okay i will
not engage with unwholesome and then the
stress and the pain of pressure will
will be there will increase
and then you realize okay what do i do
now i do the same thing
now on account of this pain and pressure
i will still not engage with anything in
wholesome including trying to get rid of
this pain and pressure because i'm so
averse to it
so the principle remains unchanged the
practice remains the same
what increases is the pressure on
account when you realize oh so it means
i'm doing it right
what happens is people take on the
virtue self-control pressure increases
and then
quickly give me a meditation technique
to relieve me of this pressure i was
like well no actually you're not
supposed to relieve yourself from it
you're supposed to not break the
precepts on account of it and that's how
you will calm down
i was thinking you know you can so you
can do all this renunciation and this
pressure is building up
it's unpleasant
and then you can't realize
but it's
it's unpleasant because i'm doing it
correctly yeah yeah
i'm cleaning it out so oh yeah i'm doing
it correctly yeah
isn't that great well that's that other
other talks we mentioned like the
pressure that's building up on account
of your renunciation is not because of
the renunciation
it's because of that which you're
renouncing
so your enunciation reveals basically
what you were under what was controlling
you reveals your addiction
abstaining from the addictive substance
causes you pain not because of your
abstinence but because of the addictive
substance that you were not noticing the
pain because you were immediately
engaging with it every time you were
pressured so it feels like there is no
problem up until i started saying no to
myself it's like saying no to yourself only has
it's like saying no to yourself only has
revealed what you were already victim of
so to speak
so in order to develop that aggregate of
virtue correctly
whether you are a layperson
or a summoner
you will also then see like the role of
patients why that patience is important
why that patience is important
not you know like not in that sense how
be patient patience is important and
it's a virtue no it's like a it's it's
it's a it's a it's a thing you can do
and develop and you you know it's useful
to remind yourself of it because
withdrawing from things that pressure
you will will will inc
will will will inc
reveal that as i said the the pain of
that pressure it will increase it
so
unless you have patience to bear it
you will then give in to that
motivation and need
in craving to get rid of it
so you might not break the precepts but
you still want to get rid of the
discomfort that they revealed
and how do you do that well you do that
by following
tradition technique
practices in that impersonal manner and
by that i mean in that like oh i just do
that because that's what we are supposed
to do i do that because that's what
technique tells me to do
so you will find ways of doing things in
that in a way that would basically mask your
in a way that would basically mask your
responsibility for it because that's how
you will alleviate the discomfort that
the virtue placed upon you so you must
actually not do that
you mustn't give in to those ways of
management even if they seemingly are
aligning themselves with the dhamma
practice the point is you are doing them because
the point is you are doing them because
you want to manage the discomfort you
don't want to endure it so in other
words you are acting out of craving
against the unpleasant feeling and
that's why you cannot be free from
craving just yet because you keep
maintaining it
so that's why virtue in itself
without uh right view without right
instruction will just be virtue you know
it will not necessarily give rise to
understanding of the four noble truths
and the way out of suffering
so the discomfort that comes on account
of virtue sense restrained self-control
is that's that discomfort
mustn't be
covered up uh
dismissed ignored ignored
or
or you know got rid of
so that discomfort must be accepted
you must be patient in regard to it
you must actually look more at your
attitude of gratuitously trying to get
rid of the discomfort then you should be
looking at the discomfort
and then if you want to practice samadhi
within that well you will realize okay
samadhi within the discomfort
not at the expense of it not instead of
it so samadhi doesn't mean disappearance
of discomfort samadhi means i am now
unmoved by any discomfort
and that's a very different thing
not necessarily externally looking by
what you're doing but internally it's
rooted in a completely different
intention one is wholesome another one
is unwholesome
so that's why that patience
is necessary for you to endure the
discomfort without habitually trying to
get rid of it
because then again you're still acting
on the level of that that sense response
pleasing give it to me displeasing get
rid of it and that's exactly what it
mean by you know even meditation is
rooted in sensuality it's still the same
principle uh so if you're patient with it able to
uh so if you're patient with it able to
endure it sufficiently enough
you will learn how to calm yourself
within it not the expense of it and of
course you will see what the true
problem is
which wasn't the discomfort there was
not the root of suffering your craving
against it was the root of suffering
so then all you need to do is recollect
the virtue
on account of which you're already
patient and contented
and you will already become regardless
of whether it's comfort or discomfort
around you
because you know exactly what not to do
and you don't need to worry about then
what should i do because you're not
trying to get rid of the pain
gratuitously anymore
just defining refining my new breath
of the same principle on from the start
yeah not engaging with anything unwholesome
not engaging with anything unwholesome
and craving isn't also
yeah so if the pain feels like oh the pain is
so if the pain feels like oh the pain is
too much
i don't know what to do well fine but
you know exactly what not to do
don't break the precepts don't
compromise the virtue
do everything else within that
don't neglect sense restraint and so on
which means okay so i don't need to do
anything as long as i don't do things i
know i shouldn't be doing that's it
and that's how you actually calm
yourself within that which which is
pressuring you and which you're enduring
because people are always pressured
internally by that what do i do how do i
react what you know what is my next move
in order to deal with this which all
carries that view
that kind of this must be dealt with and
you're burdened by that that's the pain
of it
but if you realize actually i don't need
to do anything
i know what i'm not going to do i know
what i'm what i shouldn't be doing but
that requires no effort now because i've
been following that lifestyle for a
while and then you are not burdened by any
and then you are not burdened by any
response or any any sort of figuring it
out it doesn't really matter all it
matters is to not do what you know
you're not supposed to do act out of
greater version delusion
that's a hard thing to do yeah
initially but then the more you do it
the easier it becomes